<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Spirituall wickednesse, in heavenly places, proclayming freedome to the forme, but persecuting the power: or an answer to a booke intituled, Freedom of religious worship: or, the jubilee of ordinances set forth without a name.</title>
            <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89855</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E808_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207529</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866574</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866574</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118850</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89855)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118850)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 123:E808[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Spirituall wickednesse, in heavenly places, proclayming freedome to the forme, but persecuting the power: or an answer to a booke intituled, Freedom of religious worship: or, the jubilee of ordinances set forth without a name.</title>
                  <author>Naylor, James, 1617?-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: James Nayler.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 17. 1654".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Freedom of religious worship --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118850:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Spirituall wickedneſſe, in Heavenly places, proclayming Freedome to the Forme, but perſecuting the Power: Or an Anſwer to a Booke intituled, <hi>Freedom of Religious Worſhip:</hi> Or, <hi>The Jubilee of Ordinances,</hi> ſet forth without a Name.</head>
            <p>A Booke being brought to my hand, intituled, <hi>Freedom of Religious Worſhip;</hi> or, <hi>The Jubilee of Ordinances,</hi> no Name I finde at it; yet the ſpirit <hi>I</hi> know, and from whence it hath its riſe; who ſeems to have hornes like a Lambe, but hath the mouth of a Dragon, ſpeaking great ſwelling words as though he would make fire come down from Heaven in the ſight of men, telling of great things that ſhall be, an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of Chriſt to come, he knows not when, but like the Jews, is become an open perſecuter of him, where he is made manifeſt; yet would he cover over his poyſon under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of not perſecuting for conſcience; yet by lyes and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſeeks to make him odious, becauſe of the plainneſſe of them, in whom he is: and what they doe in true obedience, he calls pretences. And out of a buſie mind, ſits as judge upon many things he knows nothing of; but what he knows natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, having not the ſpirit that was in the Apoſtles (as he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſeth) and though he have not that ſpirit wich is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible; yet judge he will, and by his judgement, all ſhall eſcape who are of his mind, or will own him for a leader; but if any doe out-ſtrip him in obedience to Chriſt, in things that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Kingdom, and beyond his wiſedom and carnall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſuch ſhall be puniſhed with whips, fines, and priſons; now though all the children of light, may eaſily judge from whence this partiall ſpirit is, yet leaſt his faire words ſhould beguile the ſimple, to take a wolfe for a lambe, I ſhall for the truths ſake, uncover his deceits in ſome few things, that by theſe, he who will ſee, may judge of the reſt; for he who is found with a lye in his mouth, cannot be of the truth, and ſuch are not to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved in matters of Faith. And thou begins thy Book, with telling <hi>what great things God hath done for this Nation, and how many houſes of ſtate and honour, and palaces of delight Chriſt hath in it.</hi> I anſwer, the firſt is true, great things hath God done
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118850:2"/>for this Nation, which being forgotten, ſhall riſe up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt it. But for the ſecond, it is but thy ſwelling words, for in thoſe thou calls his houſes of ſtate and honour, and pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of delight, they who ſee with the light of Chriſt, ſees every one hunting after his own honour and ſtate, worſhipping, and ſeeking worſhip one of another, and treading under foot hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, which is the honour of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> takes no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to dwell in ſuch palaces; and were thou not blinde, thou ſhould ſee more cauſe herein to mourn, then to boaſt. <hi>Thou tells of the work of Chriſt in this Nation; then compares it to a Picture with a double face, on the one ſide with the face of a beautifull Virgin, of the other ſide, the face of an ugly Owle;</hi> But this is thy double eye, which ſhall never ſee into the work of Chriſt, who ſayes it ſeems ugly; but this is thy confuſion, who art blinde, for who ſees into his works, witnes them holy perfect. Thou ſayes, <hi>godly men in all ages have put to their ſhoulders to uphold ſome peece of Anti-Chriſt.</hi> I anſwer, That is thy work, who would puniſh with whips, fines, and priſons, ſuch as are ſent to diſcover Anti-Chriſt, and to declare the word of the Lord in your Synagogues, and calls it <hi>diſturbance;</hi> and here thou would not hold up part, but all Anti-Chriſts Kingdom, who would not have any to diſcover him where he is; and thou who would give the title of godly to men, while they are upholding Anti-Chriſt, would put a faire colour on a wicked worke; and here thou appears to be of the ſerpent, painting the out-ſide, who would be counted God-like, but acts for the Kingdom of Satan, but ſuch godly men ſhall have their reward according to their work. <hi>Thou tells of the Scribes and Phariſces, who ſeemed to long after the comming of the Meſſias in the Fleſh, of whom they were the greateſt oppoſers;</hi> but cannot ſee thy ſelfe that Phariſee, who while thou art talking of his perſonall appearance in another age, thou knoweſt not when, art for whipping, fining, and impriſoning the bodies of them, in whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> is made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in ſpirit; and here thou art Anti-chriſt, who denyes Chriſt at preſent to be come in the fleſh, and would put him a far off, to another day, telling <hi>of glorious dayes to come,</hi> but at preſent art an enemy to him, and an open perſecuter of him, and knows not him who is the ſame Chriſt to day, yeſterday, and for ever,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118850:2"/>to all who will receive him. Thou ſaiſt, <hi>for a wicked man to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon a godly man, is tyrannicall;</hi> and yet thou would have ſome whipt, fined, and impriſoned, for obeying the commands of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which thou calls <hi>diſturbance;</hi> and here thou art that wicked tyrant, that would impoſe upon the righteous. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>all Governments are alike lawfull by Gods word.</hi> I anſwer, Gods word ownes no Government but that which is according to it, juſt and righteous; and though his ſaints may ſuffer under unrighteous governments, yet are not ſuch governments law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full by Gods word; but God hath ſent, and doth ſend his word by his ſervants to declare againſt ſuch governments; and here thou belyeſt the word of God, which is pure and juſt, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes all that is unjuſt and unholy; and by the word ſhall all Governours be judged, which word is but one, and doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with no mans will, though ſuch as thou may wreſt the letter to your own deſtruction; yet the word ſtands a witnes againſt you for ever. And thou ſayeſt, <hi>ſome blaſphemouſly queſtion who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Scripture be the word of God.</hi> I anſwer, The Scripture it ſelfe ſaith, God is the word, and the word was in the beginning before the letter was; but it doth not ſay, the letter is the word, which hath been, and may be altered, which had a beginning, and ſhall have an end; and this thou ſayeſt, <hi>is eternall:</hi> and here all that knows any thing of the word ſhall witnes thee a lyar; and I charge thee to prove, if thou canſt, that any of the holy men of God, to whom the word came, had it from the letter, or out of a Book; but they who were the falſe prophets which God never ſpoke to, ſtole what was ſpoken to others their neighbours, and called that the word, as you doe; but ſaith the Lord, I am againſt ſuch, and ſuch are falſe Prophets now, and theeves, and knows not the word, nor the doore, and God is againſt you, and you ſhall not eſcape. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>The weapons of the Goſpel are wooings, and beſeechings;</hi> and yet thou would have ſome whipt, fin'd, and impriſoned; and here thou art <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and it is not to be heeded what thou ſayeſt. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>none but the Pope and Quakers pretend a ſpirit of infallibility, ſuch as was in the Apoſtles;</hi> when as the Scripture ſaith, That all the gifts of the ſaints are by one, and the ſame ſpirit; and by one ſpirit were they all Baptized; and he that is joyned to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118850:3"/>Lord is one ſpirit; and here I charge thee in the preſence of the Lord to be a ſeducer, and Anti-Chriſt, and led by a ſpirit of error, who hath not that infallible ſpirit which was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, for whoſoever hath not that ſpirit, is Anti-Chriſt; and this is the cauſe why ſo many lyes and confuſions are found in thy mouth, becauſe thou art not guided by that ſpirit of truth, which leads into all truth which was in the Apoſtles, and in all the ſaints, but art led by thy own imaginations, and ſerpents wiſedom, from whom the things of God are hid; and thou beaſt, &amp; falſe prophet, who haſt not that ſpirit which was in the Apoſtles, by which the Scriptures were given forth, and by which the ſaints are guided; what haſt thou to doe to ſit as Judge of the ſaints? or what they doe in obedience to that ſpirit thou knows not? or to interpret any Scriptures? for no Scripture is of any private interpretation; and thou that has not that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, haſt a private ſpirit, and thy interpretions are private, and for thy private ends; and againſt thy generation is the Booke ſealed, and you ſee but the out-ſide, and out of pride and a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie mind would guide others, but are blinde your ſelves, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told of it, calls it rayling, which is the truth in plainnes, as one day you ſhall be forced to confeſſe it againſt thy ſelfe, as now thou confeſteſt in thee much darkneſſe; and yet thou wilt be judging the children of light. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>It is the marke of Chriſts ſheep to ſuffer perſecution, not to perſecute;</hi> here be thou witnes againſt thy ſelfe, that thou art none of Chriſts ſheep, who talkes of whipping, finings and impriſoning any, for obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, which thou calls <hi>diſturbance,</hi> and who would have them publikely whipped, whom God hath commanded to goe naked, as ſignes to you who live in your pride and exceſſe; and thou enemy of God hadſt thou lived in <hi>Iſayahs</hi> time, who was made a ſigne in the ſame kind, he ſhould have had no better cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from thee for obeying God, then theſe have. And thou ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, <hi>this follows their conceited perfection, the great Idoll of their profeſſion; if they be but perfect as</hi> Adam, <hi>they may goe naked as</hi> Adam, <hi>and throw away their cloathes, as they doe Ordinances:</hi> And here thou ſheweſt what ſpirit acts in thee; which of them haſt thou known to goe naked, upon that accompt, that is to ſay, <hi>perfection?</hi> or which of them have throwne away their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118850:3"/>cloathes to goe naked, but having done what they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, have put on their cloathes againe: neither doe they it of cuſtome, or by their own wills; and what Ordinances of Chriſt have they thrown away? and here I charge thee before the Lord to be a lyar, and a falſe accuſer of the brethren, till thou prove what thou haſt ſaid: and thou that calls perfection (that which God requires of all his) <hi>an Idoll,</hi> here I charge thee to be a blaſphemer, and an enemy to the commands of God, and a perſecuter of them that obey him, and the hand of God thou ſhalt not eſcape, thou envious one, who talks of whipping the ſaints, and yet for a cover would ſeem to write againſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution; O thou full of ſubtilty, thy covers cannot hide thee; which of the ſaints did ever talke of whipping their brethren, fining, and impriſoning them? And thou ſayeſt, <hi>to diſturbe any in the time of their worſhip, as the Quakers doe, is juſtly puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; never any of the Apoſtles did practice it in the Iewiſh Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, or Heatheniſh-Temples.</hi> I anſwer, any one being moved of the Lord to come into the Aſſemblyes in a peaceable way, to declare the word of the Lord, and to gather ſoules out of your Idolatrous Formes, into the worſhip in ſpirit; you that call this a <hi>diſturbance,</hi> are worſe then the Heathen, who heard the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and counted it no diſturbance; and by this means were the Churches of the ſaints gathered from among the Heathen. And thou that ſayeſt, <hi>none of the Apoſtles did ever practice this;</hi> plaine Scripture ſhall witneſſe thee a lyar; for doth it not ſay plainly, <hi>Paul as his manner was, went into the Iewiſh Synagogues three Sabbath dayes, reaſoning, opening and alledging the things of Chriſt, Acts</hi> 17 And the Apoſtles went into the Temple, and ſpake boldly, after they were threatned and charged to ſpeake no more in that name, by ſuch perſecuters as thou art, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. And here thou art proved a lyer before all people, who reads the practice of the Apoſtles and matters not what thou ſayes, true or falſe, ſo thou canſt but make the practice of the Saints odious, and thereby keep up thy falſe worſhip, that none be ſuffered to lay it open from the Lord, but calls it a diſturbance, and break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the peace, who comes in peace to declare truth; but thoſe who beate, ſtone, mocke, and ſhamefully entreat ſuch and impriſon them, while they move not a hand againſt any, theſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118850:4"/>are counted no offenders by thoſe of thy generation; but you puniſh the innocent, and lets the guilty goe free; and for this ſhall you be accountable before the Lord, when he comes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after blood. And thou ſayeſt, <hi>a carnall miniſtery may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert ſoules;</hi> whereas God ſaith, <hi>I ſent them not,</hi> and therefore they ſhall not profit the people; and here thou art one of them who holds up the falſe Prophets, and a carnall Miniſtery whom Chriſt never ſent, and ſuch did alwayes hate and perſecute the true Miniſters of God; and as thou pleads for a carnall Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſo thou holds up carnall Ordinances; but who holds up the carnall, knowes not the ſpirituall worſhip; and thou who art born after the fleſh, perſecutes him who is born after the ſpirit, and the Scripture is fulfilled upon thee. Thou ſayeſt, <hi>the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the world, have more neceſſary qualifications to all govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then the children of light; and the Iewes had a command from God, to appoint godly Magiſtrates, yet were their Magiſtrates moſt hideous oppreſſors.</hi> I anſwer, here thou ſheweſt thy propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who prefers the wiſedom of man in matters of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before the light of God; and it is plaine to all, that thou knows not the guiding of the light of God, nor the worth of it, but art contrary to God, the Scriptures, and all good men, for ſaith God, <hi>They that take counſell, and not of me, ſhall not ſtand;</hi> and all that ever governed well, had their councell from the ſpirit of God; as appears in <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> and all the Kings of <hi>Iudea:</hi> and when they took councell at any thing elſe, then they fell; and the Scripture ſaith, <hi>When the righteous are in authority, then the people rejoyce; but when the wicked beare rule, the people mourne:</hi> And ſaid <hi>David, in thy light ſhall I ſee light; and I ſet thy Law before my face, therefore I ſhall never be moved; and the Law of God is perfect, teaching the ſimple.</hi> And whereas thou ſayeſt, <hi>The Iewiſh Magiſtrates were moſt hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous oppreſſors,</hi> was that as they were godly men, and children of the light? Thou blinde ſot, doth the light of God teach op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? art not thou aſhamed to call the Scriptures, <hi>A ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rule,</hi> and yet holds out things quite contrary to it? where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſilence, thou childe of darkneſſe, who haſt not that ſpirit that was in the Apoſtles, which ſpirit gave forth the Scriptures; but by that ſpirit, and the Scripture, art thou condemned and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118850:4"/>proved a lyar. And thou ſaith, <hi>You are not yet come to the firſt reſurrection, to the new Heaven, and the new Earth, wherein dwells righteouſneſſe:</hi> And here, be thou witnes againſt thy ſelfe, and thy Church, who are yet in the fall, and habitation of unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, a cage of unclean birds, where the old Earth and Heaven is yet ſtanding; but the Church of Chriſt is an habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of holines; and where he dwells, there dwells righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, who witnes the reſurrection, and all things made new, and the old put off; and how fit, thou that art in death, and has not that ſpirit of life, and infallibility in judgement rayſed up in thee, to ſit as Iudge over the living, let all who are alive judge; for the reſurrection ſhall judge of the dead, but the dead cannot judge it; and here thou art ſhut out from all the churches of the living God, who are builded on living ſtones, but thou in death, and cannot witnes the reſurrection, and death ſpeaks in thee, and the ſerpent, and the curſe of God is upon thy head; thou that art in death, tells of great things that ſhall be from the letter, but being ignorant of the ſpirit, cannot ſee how great things are preſent, to them who can receive it; and when thou haſt done, thou begins to revile the <hi>Quakers,</hi> (the object of thy malice) and ſayes, <hi>They ignorantly and ridiculouſly affirme, that the Scriptures are fulfilled in them.</hi> I anſwer, Is not Chriſt the end of all Scriptures? and where he is come, and manifeſt, are they not fulfil'd in whom he is, who is the end of Law and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, whereof thou art ignorant, who puts it off till the next age, as thy fathers have alwayes done? but the children of light ſee him preſent now, and heare his voyce to day; but thou who denyes the light, art hardened through thy pride and riches, and cannot enter, neither would thou ſuffer others; and woe unto thee, who would ſhut up the Kingdom againſt this generation, for if thou ſhould live in the next generation, it would be ſtill to come a generation further; and here thou art the blind Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, who looks ſtill for a Chriſt to come, but reviles and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutes them where he is made manifeſt: and in thy high excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the letter, thou ſayſt, <hi>That one bleſſed notion of the Goſpel, is more glorious and raviſhing, then ten thouſand of revelations:</hi> Here thou appears to be ignorant of God, and that way by which all the ſaints ever came to know him: for Chriſt ſaith,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118850:5"/>
               <hi>None knows the Father, but to whom the Sonne reveales him:</hi> and prove if thou canſt, that ever any came to know God by noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by any other way, but by revelation. And thou ſayſt, <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Book of Revelations, let us looke for no more revelations of that kind:</hi> And here you would limit God, that none ſhould ever heare his voyce any more, but in the letter what he ſpoke to others; and I declare thee to be a lyar, and a notioniſt, by thy own confeſſion, and knows nothing of God, but what thou haſt in notion: but I witnes the voyce of God, and Revelation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which I had never known God but by heare-ſay, as thou doſt; and thou worſhips thou knows not what, who knows not God but in notion, for God is a ſpirit, and is neither known, nor worſhipped in notion, but in ſpirit; and here thou art ſhut out from the ſaints of God, who hath alwayes made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe knowne to his in ſpirit; but thy God is onely knowne in notion; and if there had been no notion, thou hadſt had no God; but our God is knowne before the letter was. And in thy next page, thou ſayſt, <hi>Its the great project of Satan in theſe dayes, to ſend out new Emiſſaries, as Waiters, Notioniſts, Quakers:</hi> And here be thou witneſſe againſt thy ſelfe, that thou art one of his emiſſaries, and ſent out by him, who art a Notio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt, whom all that wait on God (and thoſe thou calls <hi>Quakers</hi>) denyes, and out of thine own mouth be thou judged that thou art of the Devill, who art a notioniſt, and a lyar, and a falſe accuſer, as is proved in thy writing in ſundry things: And thou who art a notioniſt, &amp; haſt not the ſpirit which was in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſayſt, <hi>thou will take liberty to ſhew ſome of our Principles,</hi> and according to that ſpirit that acts in thee, ſo thou ſpeaks and takes liberty to lye and ſlander. And thou ſayſt, <hi>We ſleight the commands of Chriſt, as Water-Baptiſme;</hi> which is a lye, for the Baptiſme of <hi>John</hi> we own, and the Baptiſme of <hi>Chriſt</hi> we own, which thou knows not, who hath not that ſpirit that was in the Apoſtles. And thou ſayſt, <hi>that Water-Baptiſme binds to all other commands of Chriſt;</hi> and that is another lye, for the ſpirit binds and unites to God and his commands, and not outward water; for thou haſt had outward water, and yet keeps not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, who art a lyar and a ſlanderer, as is plainly proved, and hundreds who know us ſhall witnes it againſt thee. Thou ſayſt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118850:5"/>
               <hi>We deny the Lords ſupper:</hi> and that's a third lye; for the Supper of the Lord we own, and the Bread that came down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Thou ſayſt, <hi>We deny Church-fellowſhip, and Sabbaths:</hi> which we own the Church of Chriſt, the Church of the Firſt-borne, the pillar and ground of truth, and we have fellowſhip therein, which thou knows not, who art not come to the firſt reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and the everlaſting Sabbath we own, and are reſted from our own works; and here thou haſt added two lyes more. Thou ſayſt, <hi>We deny the fleſh of Chriſt, and the reſurrection,</hi> which we own, which reſurrection thou art not yet come to, by thine own confeſſion, and theſe make up the number of ſeven lyes; and here thou art a perfect lyar, and ſlanderer, and falſe accuſer. And whereas thou ſays, <hi>It was the maine Doctrine of the Apoſtles, that the ſame fleſh of every man and woman ſhall ariſe;</hi> here thou deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt with the Apoſtle, as thou doſt with us; where doth he ſay the ſame? but he ſaith, <hi>thou foole, that which thou ſoweſt is not the ſame that ſhall be, but God giveth it a body as pleaſeth him; it is ſowne a naturall body, it is rayſed a ſpirituall body: and this I ſay brethren, that fleſh and blood ſhall not inherit the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for we ſhall be changed,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. and here the Scripture witneſſes, that thou belyes the Apoſtle, as thou doſt us. And thou ſcoffes at <hi>immediate commands,</hi> which we own, and all the ſaints and holy men of God, ſhall witnes with us againſt thee; which of them had their commands from any other, but, from God, whoſe voyce is immediate? and they did not walk by tradition, or from the commands that had bin given to others, ſought out of the letter, as thou doſt, but had their particular immediate commands, which they obeyed. And thou ſcoffes at <hi>a Chriſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, a Word within, a Baptiſme within, a Sabbath within;</hi> and here thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe to be a reprobate, without, &amp; carnall in all theſe things, &amp; not to have the ſaints <hi>Chriſt</hi> who was in them <hi>the hope of glory;</hi> but thy Chriſt is without thee, unborn or formed in thee, and thou looks not for him till the next generation: the ſaints word was within them, in the heart, and in the mouth, and this is the word of faith which the Apoſtles Preached; but thy word is without thee in a book which is dead: The ſaints Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was by one ſpirit into one body, not the waſhing away of the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good conſcience; but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118850:6"/>thine is without, in carnall water; the ſaints were entered into the ſpirituall ſabbath, <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> but thine is without, in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of days, in the type, and ſo denies Chriſt come in the fleſh, and this is Anti-chriſt: and here thou art without in carnall ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, but the ſaints within in ſpirituall worſhip; and all who are ſpirituall, judges thee who art carnall, but thou canſt not judge the ſpirituall man, but art without in the world among the heathen, &amp; in thy imaginations, who has not that ſpirit to guide thee which was in the Apoſtles: and thou art the beaſt which haſt another ſpirit that was not in the Apoſtles, but is contrary to it, and therefore thou makes war with the ſaints, and the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet that denies the immediate voyce of God, and ſay, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> when the Lord never ſpoke to thee; and the beaſt and falſe prophet muſt into the lake, there is thy portion. Thou ſcoffes at <hi>perfection, mortification, and freedom from ſin in this life,</hi> which was the end of Chriſts comming, and that which the ſaints preſſed after, and witneſſed, and which God commands; and here thou ſhews thy ſelfe to be an enemy to Gods commands, Chriſts comming, and the ſaints practice, and to be an upholder of the Devils Kingdom, who cannot endure to heare of ſin going down, and mortification while men live, but concludes all muſt live in ſin, and ſerve the Devill while they live, and deny the Devil, and ſerve God when they are dead, for they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not ſerve both at once, and this is thy judgment, who haſt not that ſpirit that was in the Apoſtles. Thou ſayſt, <hi>we lay claime to five great points of Popery, poverty, infallibility, unity, revelations, ſelfe-righteouſneſſe, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</hi> I anſwer, ſelfe-righteouſneſſe we deny, and witnes the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt; but thou who calls poverty, infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, unity, revelation, and perfection, points of Popery, ſhews what religion thou art of, who denies poverty, when the ſaints were many of them poormen, and had no certain dwelling pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Lazarus</hi> a poor man, but thou art <hi>Dives,</hi> (reade thy figure) and counts it Popery to be poor: the ſaints were guided by an infallible ſpirit, but thou art led by the ſpirit of error, and yet out of a buſie mind, would be a Judge over the infallible ſpirit, and calls is Popery. The ſaints lived in unity, <hi>were all of one heart, and one mind, and one ſoule,</hi> and this thou calls Popery; but thou art ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> thy hand againſt every man, villifying all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118850:6"/>but thy ſelfe, and art an enemy to the ſpirit of unity, and denies thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to ſtand in unity. And the ſaints had their revelations, by which they knew God and his will: And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>No man knowes the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but he to whom the Sonne reveals him;</hi> and here thou art witneſſed that thou knows not God, who denies revelation, and calls it Popery, and haſt thy knowledge by heare-ſay from others. The ſaints wineſſed <hi>perfection,</hi> and preſſed after it, and God witneſſeth it, and Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it, which thou calls Popery, and thou might as well ſay, Chriſt taught Popery. Thou ſays, <hi>we care for beleeving no more, then that which is immediately given in and revealed to us,</hi> and this thou calls, <hi>Popiſh Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</hi> I anſwer, we witneſſe no other Faith, but what is the gift of God, and this is that Faith the ſaints witneſſe in Scriptures, and by this Faith we have received of God, doe we deny thee and thy faith which thou haſt fetcht, in which thou never received of God, which is the Worlds faith; and by this faith thou never received from God art thou given up to beleeve lyes, and tell lyes; <hi>for every good and perfect gift commeth from above:</hi> but thy faith, which is from below, is earthly, no better then the faith of Infidels, which is not received from God: and here let all take heed how they beleeve thee, whoſe faith is not given to thee of God, and thy religion is diſcovered, who beleeves that which thou never received from God; and that beleife which is not received of God, is of the Devill. And thou tells <hi>of trying the ſpirits, and things that differ, according to that great Canon of the Apoſtles:</hi> But where doth the Scripture tell of the Apoſtles Canon? but ſuch Anti-Chriſts words are moſt ſuteable to that Kingdome of Anti-Chriſt wherein thou art. And thou ſayſt, <hi>try the ſpirits, that is, hold them up in the Sun beames of Scripture, the onely touchſtone of Doctrine:</hi> but theſe are thy own words, which thou adds, by another ſpirit then that which was in the Apoſtles, by which thou would exclude that ſpirit; but thou who haſt not that ſpirit, muſt cry up ſuch as thou haſt, the letter for the ſpirit; which let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, thou haſt nothing to doe withall, who haſt not that ſpirit that gave it forth, and therefore prefers the letter before the ſpirit, and calls it, <hi>the originall of all truth;</hi> but knows not that truth which was before the the letter was written, but art a lyar, and calls the letter the Written Word, not knowing that Word from which the letter was Written; which word is ſpirituall, and not carnall, the originall of all things; and it is the ſpirit that ſearcheth, and tryeth all things, and not the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and thou who haſt not that ſpirit that was in the Apoſtles, art tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118850:7"/>how people <hi>come to fall into great evills, and of preſervatives againſt evills,</hi> but cannot ſee thy ſelfe in the great evill, and in the fall, who art not come to the reſurrection, nor the habitation of righteouſneſſe, who haſt not the ſpirit of God vvhich is infallible, nor haſt received that which thou believeſt from God; and thou who art not come to the firſt reſurrection, death ſpeaks in thee: And how canſt thou teach others the way of life? Wherefore ſilence, thou that art in the grave, with thy earnall Chriſt, carnall Word, carnall Faith, which has not received it of God; carnall Baptiſme, carnall Ordinances, and carnall ſpirit, which are all without thee: ceaſe thy pratling, thou byſie body, til thou come to witnes him who is inviſible, before all theſe carnall things were, and in vvhom they are all ſwallowed up, finiſht, and ended; for thou vvho cannot vvitnes Chriſt revealed in thee, cannot Preach him; and thou vvho cannot vvitnes Chriſt come in the fleſh, at preſent, art Anti-chriſt, and vvould be a Maſter or Teacher of others but knows not vvhat thou ſpeaks, nor vvhereof thou affirmes. And <hi>for the markes that leads into the great evill thou ſpeaks of,</hi> they are in thy ſelfe, and (blinde guide) thou cannot ſee them: and thou vvould be teaching vvayes to keep others out of evill, vvhen as thou art in the evill, and in the fall, and knows not the vvay out, nor the reſurrection: Wherefore thou hypocrite, look to the beame in thine own eye firſt, for thou <hi>knows</hi> not what ſpirit thou art of; but haſt the ſpirit of envy at the innocent, ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from a blind zeale, from vvhich thou ſpeaks evill of that thou <hi>knows</hi> not; and thou art ſet on fire of Hell, and art in the gall of bitterneſſe, and bonds of iniquity: Wherefore repent, and turne in thy minde to that vvhich vvould leade thee to doe as thou vvould be done by; and if thou minde it, it vvill ſtill thy buſie minde, and bring thee into judgement for all thy hard ſpeeches thou haſt blaſphemouſly ſpoken againſt the ſpirit of God, and his people, leaſt he take thee away in his vvrath, and judge thee according to the ſecret envy vvhich is in thy Heart, againſt his deſpiſed ones, and then had thou better never a been borne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Servant of the truth <hi>James Nayler.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is no rayling, but plaine dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and in love to thy ſoule, as one day thou ſhalt be forced to confeſſe againſt thy ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
